خب در سال گذشته در مورد مایکروسرویس ها زیاد صحبت شد
so microservices have been talked about a lot over the last year
من مطالب زیادی در توئیتر تمایل به گفتگو درباره این موضوع را دیدم
also I see a huge amount of stuff on Twitter and the like talking about this topic
این (مایکروسرویس) چیزی است که برای مدت کمی طولانی تر در موردش شنیدم
it's something I've been hearing about for a good bit for a little bit longer
دو یا سه سال گذشته همکاران و دوستان مختلفم در مورد مایکروسرویس ها سخنرانی کرده اند
last two or three years various of my colleagues and friends have been talking about micro services
و برای من چالش، امتحان کردن و شناخت صحیح  اینکه مایکروسرویس ها دقیقا چه هستند بود
and for me the struggle was to try and figure out well what exactly are they
وقتی افراد در مورد مایکروسرویس ها صحبت می کنند دقیقا منظور آنها چیست؟
what what do people really mean when they talk about microservices
و می دونید، کی باید استفاده از این تکنیک را بررسی کنیم؟
and also you know when should we consider using this technique
جدید است یا نیست؟ آیا ازش استفاده کنیم؟ استفاده نکنیم؟ و آن چیزی که در وهله ی اول نیست
is it new or not. Do we use it? do we not use it? And what not it is in the first place
منظورم اینه که ایده اولیه کاملا روشن و قابل درک است
I mean the basic idea is fairly straightforward
شما مایکروسرویس ها را در تقابل با چیزی که به عنوان برنامه تکی سنتی در نظر گرفته می شود قرار می دهید
you contrast it with what's considered to be a traditional monolithic application
یک برنامه تکی به این معنی است که شما قابلیت های مختلفی دارید
A monolithic application means you've got various capabilities,
چیزهای مختلفی که می خواهید آماده کنید
various things that you want to provide
و همه آنها را در یک برنامه مشابه قرار می دهید
and you put them all in the same application
که معمولا در یک فرآیند منفرد اجرا می شود
typically running in a single process
و شما به آن به عنوان یک موجودیت فکر می کنید
and you think of it as one thing
پیشنهاد مایکروسرویس
the microservice approach
و دستورالعمل اصلی مایکروسرویس؛ تلاش برای گرفتن هر کدام از این قابلیت ها و قرار دادن آنها در فرآیندهای مستقل است
and its crew disciplines is trying to take each of these capabilities and put them into separate processes
و بجای داشتن فقط یک فرآیند؛ این شبکه از فرآیندهای ارتباطی را داشته باشیم
and instead of having one process have this network of communicating processes
بسیاری از افراد استفاده از مثال خط فرمان یونیکس را می پسندند
a lot of people like to use the example of of the UNIX command line
جایی که اگر بخواهید لیستی از فایل ها را در دایرکتوریتان مرتب کنید، ممکن است از 2 یا 3 برنامه متفاوت استفاده کنید
where if you want to get a list of all the files in your directory sorted you might use two or three different programs
و آنها را با هم درون یک خط لوله قرار می دهید تا آنرا انجام دهد
put together in a pipeline to do so
این مورد همچنین دارای یک پیامد برای توزیع شدگی می شود
it also has a consequence for distribution
اگر شما یک برنامه تکی داشتید با برش های موثر در برنامه تکی و قرار دادن آن در چندین ماشین؛ آنرا مقیاس می کنید
if you've got a monolith, you scale by effectively cookie cutter in the monolith and putting it on multiple machines
با این وجود در صورتی که ما مایکروسرویس بودیم؛ رویکردهای منعطف تری داشتید، زیرا می توانستید
while we're microservices you've got more of a flexible approach because you can
سرویس های مختلف را بر روی ماشین های متفاوتی قرار دهید
put different services on different machines
در نتیجه در صورتی که سرویسی بار بیشتری نسبت به بقیه دریافت کند؛ می توانید کپی های بیشتری از آن ایجاد کنید
so that if some services get more load than others they can have more copies of them made
آن نوعی از یک مرور اجمالی ابتدایی است
that's the kind of very crude overview
اما هنوز راه طولانی از این مرور اجمالی تا چیزی که واقعا میخواهم تعریف مایکروسرویس ها بنامم وجود دارد
but this is still a long way away from what I would really call the definition of it
منظورم این است که مایکروسرویس ها؛ نسبت به تمام چیزهایی که از افراد در مورد معماری های سرویس-گرا از 10 سال پیش تا بحال شنیدیم چگونه متمایز می شود
I mean how does this vary from everything I've been hearing people Yammer on about service-oriented architecture for the last 10 years
اما نگرانی در مورد موضوعاتی شبیه مایکروسرویس ها این است که رسیدن به هر نوع تعریف ثابت و پایدار بسیار مشکل است
but the trouble is with something like a topic like micro services it's very hard to come up with any kind of firm definition
بله منظور اینه که مورد مشابهی با NoSQL را احساس می کنم؛ درسته منظورم پایگاه داده های NoSQL است. منظورم اینه که تعریف اون چیه و NoSQL
yes I mean I've filled the same thing with no sequel right I mean no sequel databases I mean what's the definition and no sequel
و حتی اگر بیشتر به عقب بر گردیم میدونید، منظورم اینه که تعریفی دقیق و جامعی که برای برنامه نویسی تابعی بهش رسیدیم چی بود؟
And even further back I mean you know what is the definition we come up with really solid definition for functional programming
خوب شما می دونید که موارد زیادی اینجا وجود داره که می توینید از طیف گسترده و متفاوتی انتخاب کنید
well you know there are plenty out there you can choose from quite a wide range
چیزی که من فکر می کنم اینه که بجای اینکه در مورد تعریف مایکروسرویس ها فکر کنیم بهتره در مورد ویژگی های مشترک اون صحبت کنیم
what I think is better to think about is instead of thinking about a definition to talk about common characteristics
و منظورم از ویژگی های مشترک این است که
and what I mean by common characteristics is to say
در صورتی که با گروهی از افراد که مایکروسرویس ها را انجام میدهند صحبت کنید
if you burnt the talk to AB whole bunch of people doing micro-services
و دنبال چیزهایی مشترکی باشید که اکثر آنها انجام می دهند
and you look for the common things that most of them are doing
معیار شما این است که بیشتر افراد که می گویند مایکروسرویس ها رو انجام می دهند؛ باید اکثر این چیزها رو انجام بدهند
your test is that most people who say they're doing micro-services should be doing most of these things
و من با یکی از همکارانم که یکی از افرادی است که کارهای زیادی با مایکروسرویس ها انجام داده همراه شدم
and I got together with one of my colleagues who's one of these guys has done a lot of work with microservices
و ما به مقاله ای رسیدیم که در اواویل امسال آنرا منتشر کردیم
and we came up with an article that we published earlier this year
----
those of you at the back are going to struggle with all that everything on the slides that's at the bottom because of the way the things laid out but it's out there
و من فقط می خواهم برخی از این 9 ویژگی مشترک را خلاصه کنم
and I'm just going to summarize some of these these were the nine common characteristics
که در نوشتن آن مقاله بهشون رسیدیم
that we came up with in writing that article.
و چون به اندازه کافی وقت ندارم  نمی خواهم که در مورد همه ی آن صحبت کنم
and I'm not going to talk through them all because I don't have enough time
ولی برخی از مواردی که فکر می کنم  بوِیژه بیشتر جذاب باشند را برجسته می کنم
but I will highlight some that I think are particularly interesting
در نتیجه اولین چیز این مفهوم مولفه سازی از طریق سرویس ها است
so the first thing is this notion of componentization via services
اکنون این ایده که نرم افزار باید درون کامپوننت ها شکسته شود
now the idea software should be broken up into components
همیشه در کنار و اطراف ما بوده است. ما همیشه از افراد بسیار زیادی در مورد نرم افزار بر پایه ی مولفه ها شنیده ایم
has been around again forever we always a lot of people have talked about component based software
و چه خوب می شد اگر مولفه هایی داشتید که می توانستید با آن کار کنید
and how it would be good to have components that you can work with
اما بیشتر اوقات اصطلاح مولفه مشکلات بسیاری از نظر  تعریف نیز دارد
but often the term component of course has had a lot of problems in terms of definition as well
بیاد می آورم که یک آبجکت؛ برای مولفه جایگزین شد و بنابراین
I remember a one point object being substituted for components and then
مولفه ها مجددا به آبجکت ها بر می گشتند و این بسیار گیچ کننده بود
components came back to objects again and it all got very confusing
تاکید اصلی من برای تعریف واقعی مولفه از تعریف Ralph Johnson می آید
what I focus on for a definition of component really comes from Ralph Johnson
او در مورد چیزی که ما تلاش می کنیم انجام بدهیم گفت
he said that what we're trying to do
ما سعی می کنیم نرم افزار را به روشی تولید کنیم که افراد مولفه های یک استریو را سرهم می کنند
is we're trying to build software the way people would assemble stereo components
میدونید، شما یک بلندگو، اسپیکر ؛ پخش کننده سی دی و پخش کننده ی نوار دارید
you know you have an amplifier you have speakers you have a CD play have a tape player
شما می توانید هر کدام از این آیتم ها را مستقل از یکدیگر جایگزین کنید
you can replace any of these items independently
و این چیز بسیار مهمی است
that's a crucial thing
و مطمئنا می توانید هر کدام از اینها را بصورت مستقل  ارتقا دهید
and indeed you can upgrade any of these items independently
در نتیجه در صورتی که بخواهم یک بلندگو بهتر داشته باشم؛ مجبور نیستم هیچ چیز دیگری را تغییر دهم
so if I want to get an improved amplifier I don't have to change everything else
و آن یکی از اهدافی است که برایش تلاش می کنیم
that's a goal of what we're aiming for
یک مولفه چیزی است که بصورت مستقل قابلیت جایگزینی و بهبود داشته باشد
a component is something that's independently replaceable independently upgradable
خوب در واژگان نرم افزار
so in terms of software
و مشاهده می کنیم که مولفه ها به دو شکل می آیند
and we see components to becoming two forms
ما کتابخانه هایی را که از اشخاص ثالث استفاده می کنیم فراهم می آوریم و آنها را بخشی از فرآیند خود می کنیم
we obtain libraries that we use from third parties and we make them part of our process
و تا حدودی برای انتخاب زمانی که می خواهیم آنرا ارتقا دهیم؛ انتخاب داریم
and to some extent we have then the choice of when do we want to upgrade that
آیا می خواهیم که نسخه ی جدیدی از کتابخانه پردازش کننده XML بگیریم
do we want to get a new version of our XML processing library
یا با چیزی که در حال استفاده از آن هستیم ادامه می دهیم
or do we stick with the one that we've currently got
و امیدواریم که ارتقا بر سایر بخش های برنامه ی ما تاثیر زیادی نداشته باشد
and hopefully the upgrade isn't going to affect the rest of our application too much
بسته به اینکه وابستگی ها به چه صورت شکل گرفته اند
depending upon how the dependencies are all laid out
سرویس نوع دیگری از مولفه است که در فرآیند مخصوص خودش اجرا می شود
A service is a different kind of component where it's running in its own process
و در حالی که با یک کتابخانه؛ در مورد استفاده از
and while with a library we talk using the language
توانایی ارتباطی درون زبانی؛ که ممکن است در هر زبانی که از آن استفاده می کنیم ایجاد کرده باشیم؛ صحبت می کنیم
communication facilities that we have built into whatever language we're using
با یک سرویس؛ عموما ما از توانایی های ارتباطی بین فرآیندها صحبت می کنیم
with a service we're typically using inter process communication facilities
از جمله فراخوانی های وب سرویس یا ارسال پیام یا مواردی شبیه این
such as web service calls or messaging or something of that kind
و سرویس ها برخی مزیت های سودمند را به ما می دهند؛ حتی هنگامی که تمایل به توانایی جایگزین و قابلیت ارتقا هم داشته باشد
and the services give us some useful advantages even when it tends to replace ability and upgrade ability
اگر من یک برنامه تکی را با مولفه هایی که کتابخانه هستند داشته باشم
if I've got a monolith with components that are libraries
و متوجه شوم که کسی نسخه ی جدید از مولفه که واقعا می تواند خوب باشد را بیرون داده است
and I've got you know somebody brings out a new version of a component that would be really nice
اما نسخه ی جدید فقط در جاوا 8 کار می کند
but it only works on Java 8
و من مولفه ی دیگری را درون برنامه ی تکی ام ارم که که با جاوا 8 کار نمی کند و فقط با جاوا 7 کار می کند
and I've got another component in my monolith that doesn't work with Java 8 and can only work with Java 7
چه کار کنم؟ من گیر افتادم
what do I do I'm stuck
اما در طرف دیگر اگر آنها سرویس های جدایی بودند که می توانستند در زمان اجرای کاملا متفاوتی اجرا شوند
but on the other hand with if they were separate services they would be running in completely different runtimes
و عمل کنند؛ آنها می توانستند با استقلال بیشتری جایگزین شوند
and they could operate they could be upgraded more independently
اکنون البته با هزینه همراه است
now there's a cost of course with that
اما بخشی از آن مفهوم این است که چگونه به توانایی ارتقا مستقل وابسته است
but that's part of the notion of how it ties into the independent upgrade ability
خب برای مورد بعدی
so for the next one
سازمان پیرامون توانایی های کسب و کار یکی دیگر از موضوعات مهم در چشم انداز دنیای مایکروسرویس های است
organization in around business capabilities is another important theme in the micro services view of the world
بنابراین خیلی؛ حتی خیلی بیشتر از سازمانهای توسعه
so a lot of lot even development organizations
که خود را پیرامون تکنولوژی سازماندهی می کنند
organize themselves around technology
منظورم اینه که شما آنرا در بسیاری از شرکت های بزرگ می بینید و ما DBA و گروه پایگاه داده خودمان را داریم
I mean you'll see this in a lot of big companies I'll have their D bas and their database group
که ممکن است کاملا نسبت به گروه افراد در UI که تمرکز آنها بر تکنولوژی است کاملا متفاوت باشند
that might have a completely different group of people on the UI it's focused around technology
نکته کلیدی با دیدگاه مایکروسرویس ها این است که ما باید در اطراف توانایی های کسب و کار سازماندهی شویم
the key thing with the micro services view of the world is that we should instead organize around business capabilities
و اینکه از این طریق هر تیم باید یکسری عوامل داشته باشد
and that each team should have some elements right the way through
و بصورت ایده آل مستقیما بر روی خود کاربر نهایی شان تمرکز کند
and ideally focusing directly on the end users themselves
یک مثال جالب توجه در این مورد از آمازون که
there's an interesting example of this from Amazon which is a
مطمیئنا یکی از الهام بخش های جامعه مایکروسرویس ها است وجود دارد
common certainly inspiration for the micro services community
وقتی که آنها تقسیم شدند که همه می دانند، آمازون خود را به دو تیم پیتزا تقسیم کرد
where when they divided everybody knows Amazon divided themselves up into two pizza teams
و درباره ی آن بسیار صحبت شد
and that's talked about a lot
و چیزی که کمتر در موردش صحبت شد این حقیقت بود که هر تیم
but what's talked about a lot less often is the fact that each team
مسئول راه ارتباطی مناسب با تجربه کاربر نهایی بود
was responsible for the communication right way through to the end user experience
و این ایده که باید بصورت مناسب و صحیحی با افراد در پایان متصل شد
and the idea that that should connect right the way through to the people at the end
و باید به این نکته بپردازند که چگونه این مورد بر نتایج کسب و کار تاثیر می گذارد بخش مهمی از این تفکر است
and they should be judged on how does this affect business outcomes right the way through is a very important part of that thinking
در نتیجه ما این مفهوم را داریم که خود را اطراف یکسری از ساختارهای کسب و کار تقسیم کنیم
so we have this notion of divide yourself up around some kind of business organization
و تا حد امکان آنرا بصورت یک پشته کامل ایجاد کنیم
and make that as full stack as possible
شاید وقتی که این مورد در مقام مقایسه با چیزی که اکثر مردم درباره ی سرویس ها دارند می رسد
perhaps when it comes to comparison to what a lot of people have come across in terms of services
یکی از دگرگونی های بزرگ دگرگونی در مورد داشتن نقاط پایانی هوشمند و لوله های احمق است
one of the biggest shifts is this shift about let's have smart endpoints and dumb pipes
وقتی که افراد زیادی در مورد معماری سرویس-گرا صحبت می کنند
when a lot of people talk about service-oriented architecture
آنها در مورد ایده ی داشتن یک سری میان افزار قوی صحبت می کنند
they talk about the idea of let's get some powerful piece of middle-ware
که بصورت اتوماتیک همه ی انواع کارها را انجام می دهند؛ پیام ها را مسیریابی می کنند؛ قوانین کسب و  کار را اعمال می کنند؛ همه ی انواع کارها را انجام می دهند
that will automatically do all sorts of stuff it'll route messages it will apply business rules
it does all sorts of things
این البته ESB است. گذرگاه سرویس سازمان
this of course is the the ESB the Enterprise Service bus
یا این بیشتر شبیه جعبه ی اسپاگتی بزرگ است
or is it more correctly known the egregious spaghetti box
جامعه مایکروسرویس ها با پشیمانی زیاد این مفهوم را رد  کرد
the micro-service community very much regret reject this notion
و گفت که هوشمندی ها باید به خود نقاط پایانی منتقل شود
and says the smarts instead should move to the endpoints themselves
چیزی که می خواهیم این است که همه چیز به هم متصل شود
what we want is everything to connect together
و بتوانیم به آسانی پیام ها یا ارتباط های میان آنها را مسیر یابی کنیم
and to be able to easily route messages or communications between them
اما اینها باید وظیفه ی نقاط پایانی باشد؛ جایی که تمام هوشمندی
but it should be up to the endpoints where all that smartness goes
و همه یمنطق کسب و کار به آنجا رفته است
any business logic
هر عمل مسیریابی
any routing stuff
تمام اینها باید بر اساس نقاط پایانی باشد که منجر می شود که مکانیزم های لوله کشی موثر خوب را به ما بدهد
all of this should be based on the endpoints just give us a good efficient piping mechanism
و در بسیاری از راه ها البته خود اینترنت  الهام بخش است
and the inspiration in many ways is of course the Internet itself
که بخوبی کار می کند
which works very well
بخاطر این حقیقت است که اینترنت نیازمند تقریبا مجموعه ای از لوله های احمق و ساکت است و تمام هوشمندی را درون نقاط پایانی قرار داده است
because of the fact that it needs a relatively dumb set of pipes and puts all the intelligence onto the endpoints
مورد دیگری که بسیاری از
another thing that also brings out this
این کارهای مختلف را به سرویس های زیادی می دهد مفهوم تمرکز زدایی است
variation to a lot of service stuff is the notion of decentralization
تمرکز زدایی به یک شیوه ی کلی که در آن دورنمای سرویس ها مدیریت می شود
decentralization in terms of the overall way in which a service landscape is governed
و بخصوص تمرکز زدایی در شیوه ی مدیریت داده
and in particularly decentralization in terms of data management
بنابراین اگر مجددا در مورد دنیای برنامه ی تکی فکر کنیم
so again if we think of the the monolithic world
در مورد این حقیقت فکر می کنیم که عموما تمام داده ها در یک پایگاه داده رابطه ای بزرگ قرار دارد
we think of the fact that generally all of the data is sitting in one honking big relational database
خیلی خب، این می تواند در یک شرکت نوشته شود
all right and it's often can be to write across a company
می دونید، استاندارد شرکت ما اوراکل است، یا شاید استاندارد شرکت ما db2 باشد
you know our company's standard is Oracle or our company's standard is db2
و هر چیزی درون محدوده می رود
everything goes inside box
و حتی بسیاری از معماری های سرویس-گرا
and even a lot of service-oriented architectures
در واقع بیشتر در مورد سرویس های متعدد یا کشیدن داده در داخل و خارج از یک پایگاه داده منطقی بزرگ است
it's really a lot about multiple services or pulling data in and out of one logically large database
نقطه نظر مایکروسرویس ها این است که می گوید
the micro service appoint point of view is to say now
هر سرویسی باید برای دیتای خود و ذخیره سازی دیتای خود مسئول باشد
every service should be responsible for its own data and its own persistence
مجددا این مورد دیگری است که از تجربه های آمازون الهام گرفته شده
again this is another thing that is inspired by the Amazon experience
آمازون هنگامی که به سمت یک رویکرد سرویس-گرا حرکت کرد آن قانون خود را ایجاد کرد
Amazon made that one of their rules when they shifted to a service-oriented approach
و گفت شما ممکن است هیچگاه با پایگاه داده سرویس های دیگر صحبت نکنید
and said you may never talk to another services data store
شما با سایر سرویس های فقط از طریق API آن سرویس های می توانید صحبت کنید
you can only talk to another service through its API
و این قانونی است که مایکروسرویس ها برای آن تلاش می کنند
and that's the rule that the micro service people push as well
این کار چندین مزیت دارد
now this is a couple advantages
اول اینکه درگیری وحشتناک یکپارچگی از طریق پایگاه داده را حذف می کند
first it removes this horrible mess of integrating through a database
که منجر به این می شود که تمام مشکلات پایانی در سازمان در یکجا نباشد
which causes no end of problems in enterprises all over the place
کار دومی که انجام می دهد آزاد سازی سرویس  ها است
the second thing it does it frees up individual services
تا بتوانند از پایگاه داده ای که برای آنها مناسب تر است استفاده کنند
to use a datastore that make sense to them
برای برخی سرویس ها پایگاه داده ی رابطه ای مناسب است
some services a relational database will make sense
و سایر سرویس ها ممکن است بخواهند از پایگاه داده های شگفت انگیز جدید NoSQL استفاده کنند
others would want to use one of these hot new NoSQL fancy things
و در هر مورد آنها از آن برای خود استفاده می کنند
and in which case they use it for that
اما ایده این است که انتخاب شما برای ذخیره سازی داده
but the idea is yours choice of data persistence
باید کاملا بر عهده ی خود سرویس ها باشد
should be entirely up to the individual service themselves
و همانطور که گفتم بخشی از این قاعده ی کلی تمرکز زدایی است
and that's part of this general notion as I said of decentralization
این قاعده همچنین به مواری از جمله زبانها و ابزارها نیز وارد می شود
it also goes to the point of things like languages and tools
مجددا باید توسط گروه های سرویس مختلف انتخاب شود
should again be individually chosen by different service groups
برای اینکه همه اینها کار کنند داشتن زیر ساخت اتوماتیک واقعا مهم است
to make all of this work it's really important to have infrastructure automation
در نتیجه بسیاری از چیزها مثل انشتار مداوم
so a lot of things such as continuous delivery
تکنیک هایی شبیه انتشار Blue/Green که به شما این امکان را می دهد که
techniques like Blue Green deployment that allow you to
کارها را به محیط عملیاتی بدون زمان توقف ببرید
put stuff to live with zero downtime
کارهای از این دست همچنین برای انجام این نوع کارها ضروری هستند
these kinds of things are mandatory in too in order to get this kind of stuff to work
چون شما در مورد ایجاد چیزی صحبت می کنید که باید برنامه ای باشد
because you're talking about building what would be one application
شامل یک یا دو جین سرویس
as a dozen or two dozen services
و داشتن روشی کاملا اتوماتیک برای انجام این کارها بسیار مهم است
so it's very important you have a very automated way of getting these things going
همچنین ممکن بخواهید که قادر باشید تا جعبه های جدید را بگیرید و انها را سریع به چرخش در آورید
you also want to be able to get new boxes and spin them up rapidly
مایکروسرویس ها همچنین تاکید بسیار زیادی بر روی مانیتورینگ دارند
it also puts a lot of emphasis on monitoring as well
شما باید مانیتورینگ خوب و مناسبی داشته باشید
you've got to have good monitoring
در نتیجه وقتی که مواردی دچار اشکال می شوند براحتی می توانید متوجه این حقیقت که چیز اشتباهی رخ داده است شوید
so that when things go wrong you can easily spot the fact that something's gone wrong
و می توانید از ابزارهای مانیتورینگ استفاده کنید تا به شما در اشکال زدایی آن کمک کند
and you can use the monitoring tools to help you debug it
و البته نتیجه ی این کار این واقعیت است که بطور ضمنی سرویس ها را برای شکست طراحی کرده اید
And that of course then leads into the notion that you have this explicit design for failure
اگر تصمیم داشته باشید که سرویس های راه دور داشته باشید
if you're going to have remote services
آنها ممکن است از کار بیافتند. بخصوص اینکه شما آنها را بین چندین نقطه توزیع می کنید
they're going to fail. particularly as you distribute them across multiple nodes
در نتیجه این بخش دیگری از این دلیل است که چرا مانیتورینگ بسیار مهم است
so this is another part of the reason why monitoring is so important
و البته این شناخته شده ترین سطح است
and of course it's most famous level
شما مواردی شبیه Chaos Monkey دارید
you have things like the chaos monkey
نتفلیکس یکی از شناخته شده ترین معماری های مایکروسرویس است
Netflix is one of the most well known microservice architectures
و انها ابزاری ایجاد کردند که بصورت تصادفی نودها را از بین می برد
and they built a tool that goes around randomly destroying nodes
و آنها از این ابزار برای تشخیص اینکه
and they use that in order to detect
قابلیت ارتجاعی و برگشت پذیری کلی شبکه آنها به چه صورت است
how resilient their overall network is
منظورم این است که، آنها را همیشه اجرا نمی کنم آنها در ساعات اداری وقتی که کسی باشه که مشکلات را رفع کند؛ اجرا می کنم
I mean I don't run it all the time they run it during office hours when there's somebody there to fix things up
اما این واقعیت که شما ابزاری داشته باشید که عامدانه باعث ایجاد خرابی شود
but the fact that you've got a tool that deliberately causes failure
برای کمک به اطمینان از انعطاف پذیری شما است
in order to help make sure you're resilient
من فکر می کنم این بخوبی داستان را پوشش می دهد؛ این گرایش را مایکروسرویسی ها این ابزارها را دارند
I think it encapsulate story well, the attitude that the micro service people have
و البته در هر نوع سیستم توزیع شده ای مجبور هستید که فرض کنید چیزها دچار نقض خواهند شد
and of course this is essential in any kind of distributed system you have to assume things are going to break
خب اینها مجموعه ویژگی های مشترک نا بودند
so that was our set of common characteristics
و امیدوارم کمی درک و احساس در مورد چیزهای مختلفی که مردم در مورد آن صحبت می کنند به شما داده باشم
and I hope gives you a bit of a flavor for the kinds of things that people talk about
اما اینها هنوز باعث بوجود آمدن تعدادی سوال می شود
but it still raises a number of questions
یکی از بزرگترین سوال ها این است که آیا مایکروسرویس ها واقعا معماری سرویس-گرا است؟
of which one of the biggest things is is this really service-oriented architecture
آیا مایکروسرویس ها فقط نوعی شبیه کارهایی است که برای مدت طولانی در کانتکستSOA شنیدیم
is this just the same kind of stuff that we've been hearing about for a long time in the context of SOA
اما برای پاسخ دادن به این سوال باید در اولین گام از خود بپرسیم که SOA به چه معنی است؟
but in order to answer that question you have to say to yourself well what is SOA in the first place
و بواقع فکر می کنم این در قلب مشکل است
and that is really I think at the heart of the problem
چون شنیدم که SOA به روش های مختلف؛ از خیلی راه های متفاوت و ناسازگار توسط افراد مختلف تعریف شده
because I've heard SOA defined in many different ways in many different incompatible ways by different people
برای برخی افراد؛ SOA دقیقا همان چیزی است که ما در موردش در دنیای مایکروسرویس ها صحبت کردیم
for some people, SOA is exactly what we've been talking about in the microservice world
و این دلیلی بود که ما تعدادی از افراد در جامعه ی SOA برخورد کردم
and that's why I met a number of people in the SOA community
یک التهاب و خشم واقعی در مایکرسرویسی ها
a really ticked off at the micro service people
چون نگرش آنها این است که ما همه اینها را انجام می دادیم و سالها به آن SOA می گفتیم؛ چرا شما این اصطلاح جدید را ابداع کردید و آنرا به همراه دارید
because their attitude is well we've been doing all of this and calling it SOA for years why do you invent this new term and bring it along
شما فقط کلمات را صدا می زنید؟ چون هر کسی می داند که با ایجاد اصطلاحات ما بطور شگفت انگیزی غنی می شویم
what is are you just calling words because everybody knows of course we become incredibly rich by coining terminology
امیدوارم
I wish
اما طبیعتا SOA معانی متفاوتی برای افراد مختلف دارد
but of course SOA means different things to different people
برای خیلی از افراد در جامعه مایکروسرویس ها
to many people in the micro services community
معماری های SOA در حول و حوش سازمان های بزرگ هستند و برای آنها SOA به معنی گذرگاه سرویس سازمانی است
they've been around big enterprises and to them SOA means the enterprise service bus
این به معنی است که جامعه ی افرادی که در SOA برای تنظیم استانداردها هستند  سرویس های سالم را فرض می کنند که به یکدیگر متصل هستند
it means Committees of people who are there to lay down standards the health services supposed to connect to each other
و این طبیعتا دنیای کاملا متفاوتی است
it's a very different world indeed
در نتیجه روشی که تمایل دارم در مورد آن فکر کنم می گوید که SOA یک اصطلاح بسیار بزرگ و گسترده است
so the way I tend to think of it is saying well SOA is this very broad term
و مایکروسرویس ها زیر مجموعه ای از استفاده ی SOA است
and micro-services is a subset of its usage
و ارزش اصطلاح مایکروسرویس ها
and the value of the term micro services
این است که اجازه می دهد که بر روی زیر مجموعه ی مفیدی از واژه ی SOA برچسب بزنیم
is it allows to put a label on a useful subset of the SOA terminology
به نظر من عبارت SOA بسیار گسترده است
in my view the SOA term is too broad
منظورم این است که SOA به معنی خیلی چیزهای مختلفی است بخصوص چیزهای بی معنی
I mean it means so many different things it's practically meaningless
but the value of micro services is it carves out a cut and consistent space within that
but he is perfectly fair to say
that the micro service approach has been done by people under the name of SOA for at least a decade if not more
so it's not a new technique at all
And it's perfectly reasonable that people are annoyed about it when they say Oh micro services are nothing new
that's a perfectly reasonable response
now one of the problems with micro-services as a term
And I like to stress I didn't come up with this term right I would have come up with a better term
but one of the things about micro-services as a term is that has this implication of size
and of course as soon as you say micro is that well how big is a micro service
And you actually talk to any of these people in the micro service world and they're always very reluctant to answer this question
they always say well you know it should be one responsibility
that's a kind of bogus thing to say right I can imagine payroll being one responsibility and I know that's a pretty big system
right I mean it's all size I mean it's very responsibilities are very flexible right
james lewis has this statement he says mirco services have got to be small enough to fit in my head
now James has config rate deal in his head, as it turns out
but his point is of course the survey that if you've got a service it should be understandable to a single person
that's his test for it but that's still a bit vague
I started asking around people trying to get a sense of size
people were extremely reluctant in many ways
But the way I was able to get some figure by saying well
how many people per service in your application
and I got a lot of different answers
and as you can see there's quite a spread here
Now 15 people 10 services
four people 200 services
there's quite a range of different sizes
it's certainly true that pretty where everywhere, come across the notion of the two pizza team
from Amazon is fairly well regarded
the sense that you should never have a team that's bigger than you could feed with two pizzas
I should say of course this is two American pizzas and you can feed a hell of a lot of people with two American pizzas
but I think the notion is still there
but within there's still a lot of variability
so that's the best I can do when it comes to defining micro-services for you
it's still I'm afraid pretty fuzzy
but you know that's the way things go
I think however it is it does carve out a reasonable class of systems
the next question of course is when you should use it
what are the advantages of micro-services compared to monoliths
now one big advantage of a monolith is it a relatively simple and familiar approach to use
and this is not to be underestimated
I mean I've already started hearing and trickling in stories of projects that
you know decide you know we want to use this micro-service stuff because it's so cool we want to do it
and they ended up getting themselves into trouble where they really should have built a simple model if instead
now if you look at an application and you say yeah that would work really nicely as a simple rails app
you don't want to build start building it as a micro service
because micro services introduced distributed computing
they often introduced asynchronous communication
and those are significant complexity boosters
so the monolith still has the advantage of up to a certain size at least simplicity
one of the great advantages of micro services is the ability to deploy the various pieces independently
if you want to upgrade a monolith, you've got to upgrade the whole thing
I heard the story of an insurance company where they've got one monolith that handled all their different lines of insurance
if they wanted to in to upgrade their auto insurance
they had to upgrade the home insurance
as well they couldn't do them independently
and that's a disadvantage of a monolith
you're forced to upgrade all at once
now if you're really good at your continuous delivery pipelines
I think you can make that work
but you but it's much harder than trying to upgrade and the separate pieces
and that was in fact one of the crucial reasons why Netflix went down this route
they had difficulties getting their systems being able to deploy as rapidly as they need to do
so they found that switching to a micro service approach gave them more flexibility
and this is of course very important in to an age
where we need to be able to deploy new applications not once every few months
but every week every day and often many times a day
and then we are granted your micro services that can give you a greater degree of availability
if your recommendation service goes down for some reason
you can still run your shopping cart
and this is important because what is the most important thing to Americans
shopping!
right so nothing must stop the shopping
now that availability of course comes from being handled be able to handle failure effectively
but if you've got availability what does that mean you lose
Consistency!
it's much harder to maintain consistency with micro service applications
so you embrace eventual consistency
which may or may not be a good thing depending on what where you
are and it's particularly difficult of course to get the right kind of consistent behavior
so that I can actually post an update when interacting with a web app and actually make sure that I see it
and not go where did that go did it get lost
which is the kind of thing that goes wrong when you don't do consistency well
another big issue we've modeled with the monolith is that it makes it relatively easy to re-factor particularly between modules
now with any kind of software design you want good modularity
you want to divide your software up into pieces
so that in order to make a change I don't have to understand the whole system
I can just understand one or two modules
but that means you've got to get your module boundaries right
and if you don't get your module boundaries right you've got to be able to change them
now if you've got a monolith, that kind of thing isn't too bad
you can say: Oh I need to move this object from over here in that module over there
it's not a hard re-factoring to do
in a micro-services world that becomes a hell of a lot harder
because now you're talking about these remote calls
so that's also I think one of the problems with running to monitor micro services too quickly
if you don't understand the module boundaries well
you've very easy to get a lock yourself into a pure design
and a monolith can be a good way of figuring out module boundaries are, before you actually do the split
and we said that one of the interesting things about micro-services is that they actually help you preserve modularity
a lot of people you know, like me waffle on endlessly about how important it is to have good modules
now follow bob Martin's rules, about clean, dependencies, and all the rest of it
but the reality is most systems find it hard to do it in practice
it's too easy to kind of do little end runs around and expose little things and not keep your module boundaries solid
on the other hand in a micro service world your communications are purely through your network interfaces
and it's maintained it makes it really easy to ensure you don't share mutable state
which is of course one of the best ways to get yourself into a confusion in a monolith module architecture
so in many ways micro service is kind of a discipline that forces you to keep your modularity together
and then I mean the last big advantage in micro services they allow you to go with multiple platforms
if some parts of your application stack
are best off with a traditional you know Java whatever language
you can use them in some places and then you use sort or an even experiment with say a closure on other areas
you've got the flexibility now of course you don't necessarily want to go so mad that you've got 20 services written in 30 programming languages
but on the other hand that flexibility can be very valuable
just as you don't know use JavaScript that's the one thing I really don't want anybody to do
you've got to fight back against that monster somehow
so that's the trade-offs
microservices are not straightforward route to go
in many ways I'd say if you're not sure if you've got a relatively small system don't worry about it
but on the other hand they can be an appropriate architecture in a lot of places
and we're still trying to understand what the boundaries are between them
it's still fairly early
and then the last point I want to say is
if you're going to go down the micro-service point
there are certain things you've got to make sure that you get sorted out otherwise you're going to get into a lot of trouble
you've got to make sure that you can provision new machines rapidly
if you're in a situation where it takes you a month to get a new server set up and provisioned and ready for use
you're going to have a lot of problems in the micro service world
this is of course why micro services go very nicely with cloud
if you can provision a new machine in the cloud very quickly
which is for instance what Netflix do then that allows you a lot of flexibility there
make sure you have at least the basics of monitoring
you want to know when any of your services go down
you want to know if something becomes unresponsive
or if important interactions or transactions are getting dropped on the floor
you've got to have at least a basic level of monitoring in place
and also you've got to make sure that your services
can be automatically and rapidly deployed
and you don't want to be spending two days deploying the service
it's got to be there in hours at the very least and preferably minutes
and it should be as much as possible automatic process
that's just the basics that's just for running with just a couple of certain amount of services
and to do more you've got to add more
there's a whole bunch of other stuff that you've got to get into play as well
so make sure you've at least got those basics
On the one I missed DevOps culture
that is you've got to break down the barriers between the operations group in the applications group so that they're working together
if you've got a difficult communications between the two again you're not going to be able to manage the quantity of services that you've got to deal with
so as I said those I think are the minimum things to have, when you first go live
you don't necessarily have to have them when you start building
but you definitely have to have them when you go live with this thing
so that's microservices
a very brief introduction
I've written various things on it there's tons of stuff out there on the web
you can go and find out more and that's the end of my first talk